caring for the old on the United Nations Population Fund's India Ageing
Report.
2023 India must attune its policies to ensure the elderly
live a life of dignity.
A good part of the world's population is growing older and India mirrors this
trend as well.
The reality According to the United Nations Population Funds India Ageing report
2023 is that the population above 60 years will double from 10.5% or
14.9 grow as on July 1st 2022 to 20.8% or
34.7 grow by 2050 with one in five individuals
said to be a senior citizen,
there will be implications for health,
economy and society.
In Kerala and West Bengal,
for instance,
there is a growing population of the elderly who live alone as Children migrate for better
opportunities,
with life expectancy increasing thanks to better ways to fight disease and decreasing
fertility rates In many countries,
including India,
there are challenges in nurturing and expanding elderly population.
Within this macro phenomenon,
there are myriad other data of importance.
For instance,
women elderly citizens outnumber their male counterparts at
60 years a person in India may expect to live another 18.3 years,
which is higher in the case of women at 19 years,
compared to men at 17.5 years.
If women in India their labour force participation is low at 24% do not have
economic and social security,
they will become more vulnerable in old age.
There are also significant interstate variations.
Most states in the south reported a higher share of the elderly population than the national average
in 2021 a gap that is expected to widen by 2036.
While states with higher fertility rates such as Bihar and Uttar Pradesh expect to see
an increase in the share of the elderly population to by 2036 the level will
remain lower than the Indian average.
Overall,
more than 2/5 of the elderly are in the poorest wealth,
Quil,
ranging from 5% in Punjab to 47% in Chattisgarh.
Also,
18.7% of the elderly do not have any income.
A high proportion of the rural population is among the elderly and often economically
deprived.
To meet the challenges physical and mental health,
basic needs of food and shelter,
income security and social care.
A whole of society approach is required.
Geriatric care must be fine tuned to their unique healthcare needs.
There are several schemes targeting the elderly,
but many are unaware of them or find it too cumbersome to sign up.
The national policy on older persons 1999 and the Maintenance and Welfare of
Parents and Senior Citizens Act 2007 laid down the care of the elderly.
But to ensure that senior citizens live in dignity,
public and private policies must provide a more supportive environment.